All right, so I guess we can get started, uh, this is the third part of uh
the lecture on energy based models
uh, which we are we're going to continue a little bit what we talked about last time on sparse coding and
talk about
GANs, very briefly. You'll hear more about it tomorrow from
Alfredo and then talk about learning world models and similar things
Also about a bit of a little bit about exotic
self-supervised and unsupervised learning algorithms
That are kind of, you know active research topics at the moment
so one thing I talked about last time was sparse coding and
i'm going to mention just a
very simple idea which consists in sort of
Combining
uh
sparse coding or the audio sparsely encoder with uh discriminative training
So imagine that the architecture i'm showing you here
uh, the the encoder if you will the the first, uh,
part on the left
Is uh mostly
Uh similar to the encoder I talked about for the the lista method
So you start with the x variable you run it through a matrix
Then you run that through a non-linearity. It could be a ReLU for example, this is the case here
And then you take the result
multiplied by
some matrix, which we're going to learn at this with the
Product of the input by the encoding matrix "We" and then pass this to a non-linearity and you can repeat this little block
This green block here multiple times. Each of those is a layer basically that consists in
A matrix or a bunch of convolutions, uh, in addition with uh, some, you know, pre-existing variable and a non-linearity
so this is you know, a funny kind of neural network where you have kind of uh,
skipping connections
And then we're going to train this neural network to do
uh, three different things or with three different criteria one criterion is going to be
Uh just reconstruct x, okay. So there's going to be a decoding matrix. That is uh,
Going to reproduce the input on the output
And we're going to do this by just minimizing squared error
So this is what's indicated by the decoding filters here
And again, this could be convolutional or not depending on which version you
you like
there's going to be an l1 criterion on the
on the feature
Vector that makes it sparse. So this is very much like a sparse auto encoder of the type that we talked about last week
but then we're also going to add a third term and this third term is going to be basically a
a simple linear
classifier
which
Is going to try to predict a category. Okay, and we're going to train the system to minimize all three criteria at the same time
So this is a sparse autoencoder that also tries to find codes that do a good job at prediction
And this is sort of a good way you can you can see this in two different ways
You can you can see this as an auto encoder that is biased towards producing good labels, or you can see this as a classifier
Multi-layer classifier that is regularized by an auto encoder. What's the advantage of this? Well the advantage is that by
Forcing the system to find representations here at the second last layer
that uh can reconstruct the input then you're basically
Biasing the system towards extracting features that contain as much information about the input as possible
So that sort of
Makes the features richer if you want it forces the system to
Not generate degenerate features, but to generate features that contain as much information as possible about about the input
That works pretty well. I think it's an underexplored method for
training neural nets
um
Because very often we don't have enough, uh label training data
or when the
The training data is such that you don't have a lot of categories
Um to work with maybe it's a two or three or ten classic problem, which we know
Tend to produce very generic degenerate features, uh in a neural net as we discussed last time
Then forcing the system to reconstruct basically
Tells it, you know, you can't generate features that are too
Degenerate or so degenerate that uh, you can't reconstruct the input from it
So that's sort of a good you could think of it as a good regularizer
Okay, group sparsity and structured sparsity so there's some work going back about 10 years, maybe a little more
Uh, in fact the first work on this are about 20 years old
On the idea of group sparsity. What does that mean?
um, here is here is the idea the idea is to train a system to generate sparse features, but not just
Normal features that are extracted say by a bunch of convolutions and ReLUs
But to basically produce sparse features that are sparse after the pooling
Okay, so you essentially have a system that consists of convolutions non-linearity and pooling you try to make those features sparse
And there's a number of different work
The idea goes back to Hyvarinen and Hoyer in 2001, uh in the context of ICA independent component analysis
And then there were you know a few other papers one by Osindero in Geoffrey Hinton's group
um
And then Kavukcuoglu who was a student of mine back in the late 2000s
Uh Karol Gregor who was post doc with me, Julien Mairal who is in France and a bunch of other people
on on this idea of structured sparse coding
so the idea basically is you take um
Uh, so some of those uh models only have an encoder
Some of them only have a decoder and some of them are auto encoders, right?
So the one on the left, Osindero's model is an encoder only model
Mairal's model is a decoder only model and
Kavukcuoglu's model is uh, basically an autoencoder a sparse autoencoder of the type that we talked about last time
um, so
How does that work? Uh, let's take
Say an encoder only model
you have a feature extractor which consists of convolutions or maybe just uh
fully connected, uh
matrices over a patch an image patch for example
And then instead of forcing the output of this to be after a non-linearity instead of forcing that to be sparse
You you put a pooling layer and you you force the pooling to be sparse
Uh and this applies to uh, all three of those
um
So here is a more specific example. This is the the version that uh, Kavukcuoglu
uh did for his phd thesis where
he had a
sparse auto encoder so you have an encoding function Ge of We Yi
it could be multiple layers in this case. It was basically just two layers
Uh with one non-linearity you have a decoder which in this case was linear. Wd times z you have a latent variable z
And that latent variable instead of going to an l1
It goes through
Uh, basically an l2, but it's l2 over groups, right? So you take
a group of components of z
You compute the l2 norm not the square to norm, but the l2 norm which means the square root of the sum of the values
of those components
Uh of the square of those components, right?
So take each component compute the square and then compute the sum of a group
Of those squares and then compute the square root of that. So that's the l2 norm of that within that group
And then you do this for multiple groups. The groups can be overlapping or non-overlapping
And you compute the sum and that's your regularizer. That's your sparsity regularizer. So what does that tend to do?
it tends to
Basically turn off the maximum number of groups. Okay, the system basically is sparsity
on groups
So it wants the smallest number of groups to be on at any one time
But within a group because it's an l2 norm within a group
It doesn't care how many units are on within the group
so
Many units can be on within a group. So what does that do?
It it forces the system basically
to
group within a pool features that turn on
simultaneously, right
So if you have features that are very similar feature extractors that are very similar filters that are very similar in a convolutional net
then those features will tend to kind of uh
When you do the training, they'll try to group themselves within a group
Because they will tend to be activated together. That's the best way to minimize the number of groups that are activated at any one time
So to get those those interesting kind of pictures here the way this was obtained is by
Here the groups, so what you're looking at here are the
Either the uh, I think it's the decoding matrix. So these are the
the the columns of the wd matrix, um that we can reconstruct an image patch from
the
sparse code by
multiplying by that matrix
But what we do here is that we group those features into blocks of 36
So we arrange all the features in a 2d map that has nothing to do with the topology of the image
We could choose any topology we want. In fact, this is not actually a 2d topology. It's a it's a toridol topology
So the left side touches the right side on the top touches the bottom
So it's topologically identical to taurus
And what we do is we
we group
Sets of 36 features within a group. Okay and those uh
Groups of 36 features overlap by by three columns and three rows. Okay, so we have multiple groups of 36 features six by six
shifted by three
You could think of this as kind of pooling over
Feature, but not pooling over space because there's no space here. It's a fully connected network
But it has a bit of the flavor the same flavor as pooling except here you pool over 36 features
You don't pool over space. All right
so
So then you you compute the sum of the l2 norm of the the features that are within each group
And that's the regularizer you use when you train your your sparse autoencoder
So the system uh wants to do is minimize the number of groups that are on at any one time
And so as I said before it
basically
It regroups all the features that are similar and likely to fire simultaneously into into groups
and because the groups overlap then it creates those kind of slowly evolving sets of features that sort of
Uh seem to kind of swirl
around
a point
So the features you get as a result of this have some sort of invariance and they have some invariance not to
Shift but to things like rotation and scale and things like that, whatever the system decides
So here the reason for choosing a 2d topology is basically just for you know to make it look beautiful
but uh
You could you could choose any kind of topology you want what is on the x-axis and the y-axis here in this diagram?
So those are arbitrary axes
I have
I don't even remember how many features there are here. This this might be 256 features. I think it's 16 by 16. So there's
256 uh hidden units, right? So imagine a network that has a 12 by 12 input patch, okay
An input image. It's a patch from an image
and
256 uh hidden units
With a fully connected full connection, uh non-linearity and there is uh another layer on top
Um, then that's the encoder and then you have uh, this group sparsity and then the the decoder is linear
Okay, and what you're seeing here are the columns of the decoder
And they are organized in a 2d topology
Okay, but it's arbitrary. Each of these squares is a column of the decoder
Each of these square is a column of decoder that also corresponds to a component of z. Okay a component of the
for the feature
the future vector
And so they are organized in a 16 by 16 matrix, but it's kind of arbitrary
We just you know, put them in a in a matrix and then we train
and because uh the groups
Take kind of six by six neighborhoods in this topology the system
naturally kind of
Learns features that are similar when they're nearby within this topology
All right
But again, I could have chosen any kind of topology
1d2d 3d or even some graph
Neighborhood of some kind as long as the pooling is, you know between neighbors on the graph that's that will work
So what i've done here is going to repeat this this little
Pattern um to kind of show uh, because it's you know, it's toroidal, uh to show the
You know how those those those patterns kind of repeat and are sort of periodical
and
the reason for visualizing it this way is that this is the kind of stuff that neuroscientists observe when they poke electrodes in the
usual primary visual cortex of
Mammals but most most animals that have good vision
They see kind of those kind of swirling patterns where neighboring
Neurons detect similar features which means similar oriented edges they are sensitive to oriented edges and and neighboring
Neurons are similar are sensitive to similar angles
Or the same angles that similar scale or or things like that
and so
Perhaps this is how you know, the brain organizes its uh, its neurons. It's by kind of
Basically having some sort of criterion on the complex cells which are the equivalent of the pooling
units that we're seeing here
Um, here is the another example here so this one is
uh not
At the patch level but it uses local connections, but it's not convolutional in the sense that it doesn't use, uh shared weights
The reason for doing this is to have some you know, a semi-realistic
uh
sort of correspondence to
a uh, uh, sort of biological
Learning where of course, you know neurons in the brain cant share weights, right? They
um, they end up being similar because you know, they train using some sort of
unsupervised learning but
There is no such thing as as weight sharing in the brain
as far as we know. so it was asked if the uh
if whether a similar strategy of the training of the autoencoder with the
Classifier and the regularizer can be applied for a variational autoencoder and whether this has been explored
if it works as well for the first slide you show
yeah, so, um, you're basically
Adding noise in a variational auto encoder and forcing sparsity
are basically two ways to achieve the same purpose which is reduce the capacity of the
Of the latent variable reduce the capacity of the of the code that is extracted by the autoencoder
And this is what prevents the system from running a trivial identity function, which would not be useful
Right and what we talked about the last couple times is the fact that if you reduce the information capacity
of the latent variable of the code
You uh as a consequence, you also minimize the volume of space that can take low energy
Okay, because you limit the number of configurations
of the code
And so as a consequence, you kinda limit the volume of space that can take low energy
so essentially this idea of
Regularizing with l1 or sparsity or something like this or adding noise to a code where limiting the norm of the code
Achieves the same purpose which is limiting the capacity of the of the code for the purpose of limiting the volume
Of space that can take low energy and as a consequence
If you train part of the space to have low energy by minimizing the reconstruction error on your training samples
Automatically the rest of the space will have higher energy because the capacity the volume that can take low energy is limited
um, so this is
Uh, just to recap uh, we talked about last time and and a couple weeks ago. This is to
This is sort of the alternative
so those kind of architectural methods are alternatives to the
contrastive methods where you explicitly push up
on the energy of bad samples
Which means you have to come up with a good idea, you know a good way of generating bad samples in that case, okay?
so again
Remember those two types of methods contrasting methods you push down the energy of the training samples you push up the energy of stuff outside
either by corrupting the original samples or by doing, uh
Uh gradient noisy gradient descent, you know contrasting divergence things like this or by generating contrasting points in some way
um, we've seen a bunch of different contrasting methods and then the alternative is
Limiting the capacity of a code, uh, or or
Kind of limiting the volume of stuff that can take low energy in the context of autoencoder or predictor
This means limiting the capacity of the code
And there are many ways to do this. one way is through sparsity one way is through adding noise while limiting the norm
That's ---
And there are other ways that we'll we'll talk about in a minute. whenever you were talking before about the group sparsity
Uh, you are summing
Just a few samples like a few indexes within a small range. What is that pj maybe I didn't pj is a group
It's a pool
so imagine this is a pool like in a convolutional net but the pool instead of
pooling just over space it pools over features as well. Okay
For a fully connected network. It just pools over components of the just features
Okay. So pj is like a set of indexes. pj is a subset of uh indices of z of components of
Z yeah. okay, Thanks
Right so here pj
Is a group of six?
components of z that happen to be
neighbors in this topology
Okay
And that's that's one p and the next p is
a similar square six by six square shifted by three pixels to the left to the top or
Uh or bottom, okay, okay
Bottom, okay. Thanks
So the overlapping between the groups is what kind of uh
Represents this topology if you want, okay
Okay
So in this this experiment, you know is is very similar to the one we just uh talked about except here, um,
We have local connections. So we have an input. It's a two-dimensional input here. We kind of only represent a 1d version of it
And and we have
Units, uh, possibly multiple units at one location. Uh,
Looking at a piece of the input kind of a local patch on the input
and then those sets of units are
Kind of, you know replicated, uh multiple times but there's no shared weights
Um, so the the units these kind of units everywhere on the input, but they the weights are not shared. Okay, they're just locally connected
So I guess i'm not quite understanding the
Overall concept of the of feature
Pooling. Um
I mean if I think about it in terms of like pooling that we used in in convolutional networks than it is
straightforward, but I don't really understand how we
how
feature pooling works
Okay
Let me let me draw a picture, maybe that'll be clear. Okay, so you start with an input vector
Okay multiply by
a matrix or pass it through uh, some sort of uh,
Encoder right which may have ReLUs and whatever or multiple matrices inside
Okay, maybe multiple layers and you get a feature vector
Okay, so let's call that
z
and now
And now you do you do pooling essentially so you divide this into groups in this case are non-overlapping
and you compute the
Within one of those groups
You compute the square root
of the sum of the squares
Of those zi's where i belong to the group
,the pool okay. It's called p because it's a pool
Okay, and you do this for all the groups
Right. So what you get here?
This output here looks very much like the output of a pooling layer in the convolutional from that. This is not a convolutional net
Okay, it's a fully connected network here
But the result is the same
And that's your that's your regularizer now in the example I just showed
You take the z?
And this is what you send to
a decoder matrix
from which you reconstruct
The input. Okay. So this is y this is y bar that's a prediction for the reconstruction and this
this pooled layer here is is only used
to
Compute the regularizer. It's not actually used as uh for reconstruction you reconstruct from the sparse code directly
but it is it looks very much like a pulling layer now if this were
uh if this were a a convolutional net
Then that that dimension
over feature here would be
Features, but you would have multiple feature maps
Okay, so i'm representing the feature dimension vertically
Then the encoder would do multiple convolutions and would also generate multiple feature maps. Perhaps a larger number
And then the kind of pooling we would do here
Is a pooling where so each
After pooling we would take
A window over space as well as over features
And compute the square root of sum of the square there and that gives us one output in our pooling
output
And then we have multiple groups of features like this that go into different
pooling so it doesn't matter whether this is convolutional or not in convolutions, you would pool over space as well as
feature type but um
If you don't have convolution you just pool over features and that, you know builds invariants to whatever it is that
Uh, the system thinks make sense
Is that clear does that answer your question? yeah, I think it's it's more clear. Thank you
Um, I have a question for when you do when you split the z into groups and do the pooling would those groups overlap
Right. So, uh in the example I showed here they do not overlap
But you can make them overlap. Okay, so
so let's say we have a feature vector z
I can
Take a pool here and a pool here and a pool here and here those groups overlap
And if I do this and I do group sparsity
where these other groups what's going to happen is that
I'm going to have sort of a continuously varying set of features here that sort of vary from one end to the other
Because the system is going to want to group within a pool features that are similar
And so because of the overlap it's going to sort of continuously vary them so that they change slowly
over the vector now
Uh in the pictures that I showed in the slides
Uh instead of organizing the the z features here in a 1d topology,I organized them in a 2d topology
And I made the groups 2-dimensional right? So I take a six by six block
uh, that's one group and then the next group will be another six by six block with some overlap and then the next group will
be
Yet another six by six block
Okay, and maybe I have an another one because I have a troidal
topology that takes these guys and these guys
Okay, and then there is you know the similar thing kind of
um
You know sliding up et cetera. So the groups basically
Are those six by six windows that are shifted by three and and overlapping
And so that's how you get those sort of continuously varying
uh features, uh along the along the dimension the two dimensions I could have equally well, uh chosen to
Organize this into in a 3d topology
Or into some sort of tree right? So I I take all the components of z
And I organize them in some sort of graph. Perhaps a tree
So this is called structured sparsity not group sparsity anymore well depends how you do it I guess
And then the groups would be things like, uh, this would this would be a group
And then perhaps this would be a group as well
Uh, and I can organize a group in sort of uh
russian dolls like this
uh, and uh
What's gonna happen there Is that the the groups
That um, the units that are in many groups will tend to be very sparse
Whereas the groups the units that are in a few groups will tend to be less sparse
and so if you do something like this with a tree
What happens here Is that the the feature in the center tends to be not sparse at all?
It's going to be something that really sort of detects just you know, very sort of generic features
And then at the first level in the tree, they're going to be a little sparse
So they're going to be sort of very sort of smooth
edge extractors or something like that and then the more you go inside of the tree the more
each feature enters
In a large number of pools and therefore they get more uh pressure to be sparse
And so they end up being much sparser, which means they end up being more selective for particular
features
And what happens there? Is that when you show an image it tends to favor
activating features that are along
Uh one particular branch in that tree
Because that's the best way to sort of minimize the number of pools that are on at any one time
So that's called structural sparsity
And there's a number of papers, uh on this by
Julien Mairal, so this this goes back about about ten years ago
and Rodolphe Jenatton
I mean they co-authored this senior author was Francis Bach
I really I put the reference in one of the slides
And there's a paper by my group also by Arthur Szlam
Which
I'll go to in a minute
Can you explain why grouping regularization actually helps in grouping similar features?
Well, so that's a good question. Uh, where first of all does it help?
and
Uh, and the answer is not clear
so
Those experiments were done, uh quite a while ago before the computation was really available and the data was available
Uh for for this to really kind of work at a big scale. This was mostly
Uh viewed as uh, the people interested in this were interested in two things
They were either interested in unsupervised learning for things like image restoration and stuff like that. This was what Mairal was doing
um
or they were interested in uh
Uh unsupervised self supervised pre-training because at the time the data sets were very small for for training. Uh,
Uh convolutional nets they were too small so they had to be some sort of pre-training procedure
Which is what I was interested in and so it's the same motivation that we now have again for self-supervised learning
But a lot of those methods haven't been brought back to the fore
They tended to work very well when the data set was small
Um, so they tended to kind of improve performance
of uh, let's say a convolutional net if you pre-trained this, uh, using a method
so using a method very similar to the one I
I uh, I showed earlier so something a bit like this but convolutional
So make the the encoder and the decoder convolutional and
Uh and and train with good sparsity on complex cells
and then after you're you're done pre-training this
uh the system you get rid of the decoder you only use the encoder as a feature extractor for uh,
Say the first layer of a conventional net
And you stick a second layer on top of it. Okay, so let me go through this a little bit
So you start you start with a with an image?
You
You have an encoder which is basically a convolution, uh Relu
Not much more than that, okay just combination value, uh
There needs to be some sort of scaling layer afterwards for for this particular case
And
You you train with group groups sparsity so you have a linear decoder
And you kind of reconstruct the input and you have a
You have a criterion here which is this group l1
Okay, so it's sum of a group sorry I call the good p right
Sum of a group a square root of sum for I in the group of z I squared
Okay, so that's good sparsity so you train this little uh sparse, uh auto encoder with group sparsity
And then what you do is you take the
Sparsity layer that you just used as a regularizer
And so you basically eliminate, um
You cut this part out of the network you take the group sparsity which is really a pooling layer an l2 pooling layer
And you stick it here
Okay, so this is basically l2 pooling
But it has the same architecture as the one you use for the
Um, you know for the groups the group sparsity
And then you use that as a feature extractor
Okay, which is like it's like the first pair of layers of a convolutional net convolutional value pooling okay with this l2 pooling not max pooling
and then you can repeat the process you can train another
Instance of this network have a couple layers here
I'm going to
and
have a
decoder
Have this l2
uh
pooling and sparsity criterion train this to reconstruct its input
And then stick the pooling on top
Eliminate this and now we have you have a pre-trained two-layer convolutional net
Okay, this is a procedure that some people call stacked auto encoder
okay, so you train an auto encoder to extract features and then you
And then you generate features with the encoder of that part of that
Of the auto encoder and you stick another layer on top train that as an auto encoder and then keep going
and the only characteristic here is that this autoencoder is trained with uh,
you know to produce invariant features through
Group sparsity essentially. we use all possible sub-trees as groups in the previous example
Uh, no, that's kind of up to you, really
What structure you use here
You can use multiple trees you can use if you want multiple features to kind of uh to represent
An input even at the low frequency, so that's really up to you
um
You know, it could be like what you can afford
uh, what you can do also is train the system with you know,
A bigger tree than necessary and then sort of prune the tree whenever there are branches that are not used or used very rarely
Okay. So this is a the experiment I showed here is uh similar, but there's only local connections and no no weight sharing
And what you see here is this again this organization of the features
In terms of what neuroscientists call pinwheel patterns. So pinwheel patterns. Are those patterns where the
uh, orientation selectivity varies continuously as you go around one of those red dots
So you take one of those red dots and if you kind of do a little circle around the the red dots
What you notice, is that the orientation
Of the feature of the edge extractor kind of varies continuously as you move around
And those are called pinwheel patterns and they are observed in the in the brain
In fact those pictures here on the right come from neuroscience papers
That describe this where the the the color here encodes the orientation set activity
And the little stars indicate those
Kind of the singularities here the the center of the pinwheel. Is the group sparsity term trained, uh to have a small value
Well, it's a regularizer, right?
let me
go back to the
Um, it's a it's it's a cost function during training or during inference depending on whether you use the
The sort of predictive version of it where you have latent variable or not, but um, but it's basically just a
it's basically just a
Term in the energy, right?
So
The term itself is not trained it's fixed right? It's just the l2 norm over groups and the groups are predetermined
Uh, but because it's a criterion it sort of determines what the
What the encoder and the decoders will do what type of features will be extracted
Here is um
another example of a sort of you know exotic way of doing
Sparse coding through lateral inhibition and there's a bunch of different ways to do this that people are proposed
This one came came from uh
uh, carol Gregor and Szlam in my lab about 10 years ago and
So here there is again a linear decoder with a square reconstruction error
This is wz minus x where x is the input here in this case
and then there is a criterion in the energy which is uh
the vector formed by the absolute values of z
Transpose times some matrix times the vector itself. So it's an um, a kind of a
quadratic form
Uh that involves z and this matrix s and the matrix s is
Either determined by hand
or
Learned so as to kind of maximize this term, okay
And
if the terms in uh in s
Are positive and large if one particular term s i j is large
What that means is that the system does not want zi and zj to be on at the same time
Okay, it wants the if zi is on
And s i j is large then it wants zj to be off and vice versa. Okay
And so it's sort of a mutual inhibition people use people call this lateral inhibition, uh in uh in neuroscience
Uh, it's basically, you know
All your feature vectors basically inhibit other feature vectors through this matrix s you can decide that the matrix s a priori is structured
So you can decide that only some terms are nonzero. You can decide that some terms those terms are fixed
Or can be trained and the way you train them is by actually maximizing
uh, so it's kind of adversarial training a little bit you you try to find the
The value of s that sort of you know, uh is as large as possible if you want within limits
Above a certain value of sij one of the z
One of zi or zj is going to go to zero and that term is gonna disappear. So the system is gonna you know,
maximize the sijs until
Uh, it's large enough to kind of do the mutual inhibition between zi and zj
And it's not going to go any further because it doesn't need to
And again if you organize s
In terms of a tree so so here
The the lines represent the the zero terms
Uh in the s matrix and whenever you don't have a line between two features
There's a there's a non-zero term in the s matrix, right?
So every feature inhibits all other features, except the ones that are up the tree or down the tree, uh from it
Uh, and this is very much like group's sparsity a little bit it's kind of the
uh
kind of the converse if you want of group sparsity instead of
saying
Features within a branch of the tree need to be activated together by minimizing, you know
l2 minimizing the number of such groups that are on here you explicitly
have a sort of inhibition term that
for every every
feature inhibits all other features in all the other branches
of the tree
And what you see again, is that you see this
Systems are organizing the features in a more or less in a continuous fashion
um
and
in such a way that features along a branch of the tree correspond to basically the same feature but with uh,
sort of different levels of selectivity
And then features along the periphery sort of vary more or less continuously because there is you know inhibition
Not just at the bottom level but also at the middle level
Okay, so to uh to go back to this the way you train the system is uh at each iteration you give an x you
Find the z that minimizes this energy function. So you find a z that reconstructs but also
Minimizes the second term which means that if you have an sij term, that is nonzero
It wants either zi or zj to be zero or at least very small
you do one step of gradient descent now to
Uh turn to kind of update w
so as to minimize the reconstruction error and you do also if you want you can do one step of
gradient ascent to make the terms in s
larger
By kind of computing the gradient of this energy with respect to s but then going up the energy not down
Uh again, if you use a not a tree but sort of some sort of 2d topology
You also get those kind of those kind of patterns
And more complex ones if there are kind of multiple scales for the features
Okay so so much for sparse coding and structured space coding
and the reason i'm i'm telling you about this is because
Uh, although those don't have a huge amount of practical applications the sparse coding
They in my opinion, uh
will be the basis for kind of
self-supervised running methods
Of the next few years as I told you I think self supervised learning right now is the hottest topic in nlp
Uh, and it's becoming kind of a bit of a hot topic in computer vision as well
And it's mostly now dominated by contrasting methods
But I think uh, the architectural methods are going to take over because contrasting methods don't scale very well
So this is sort of you know giving you weapons for the future if you want
Understanding what this is all about
Um, okay now for something completely different this is something that Alfredo will like because he works on this project
And it's one of the uses probably one of the most important uses of self supervised learning is the idea of
learning world models for control systems or for other purpose
So
um
when we
when humans or animals learn a task
We quite obviously have a kind of good internal model of how the world works
Of intuitive physics of the fact that when an object is not supported it falls
We've learned gravity when we were babies probably around the age of nine months or so eight or nine months
That's when it pops up in babies
Um, and we learned this mostly about observation
So how is it that we can learn how the world works and all the concepts about the world?
by observation
and there are
There are two reasons for this right?
So one I already explained is the idea of self supervised learning if you can train yourself to predict. Maybe you will
spontaneously kind of learn abstract concepts about the world
That might be useful
in preparation for running a particular task
or a set of tasks
But there's another reason which is that
You actually want to build models of the world if you want to be able to act on the world
right
so
I'm holding this pen and I know that if I move my hand up
the the pen will move with it because you know
It's between my fingers. I know that if I open my fingers the pen will fall. I know by gravity I know by grasping
Uh, i've learned all that stuff and i've learned mostly about observation
I've learned also by experimentation, but a lot of what I learned I learned just by observation
So the big question is can we learn can we
use
What we've learned about self-supervised learning to train a system
to learn world models
Um, and what is a world model, okay
So if you if you want to sort of give the an idea of the architecture of an autonomous intelligence system
It would be a system that is composed of essentially four major blocks here that are represented on the left
So it's an intelligent agent or maybe not so intelligent. We'll see
it has a perception module and the perception module basically observes the world and then
computes a representation of the state of the world
Okay
Called s(t) At time t s of t is the
the
Idea that the system has of the state of the world
This is necessarily an incomplete representation of the world because we can't observe the entire universe at once
We only observe what's immediately around us and even that we can't see
through occlusions and there is a lot of
You know internal states about the world that we can't observe well enough
Even if you can observe your accuracy or observation may not be good enough
So if I put this pen in my in my hand
And it appears to be vertical and let it go
It's going to fall but you can't really predict in what direction i've used that example before
to describe the problem of
Alliatoric, uh
uncertainty, which is the world is non-deterministic and you can't predict exactly what's going to happen because
you don't have a perfect reading of thestate of the world
And maybe the world is intrinsically stochastic
We don't know that actually
Okay, so a forward model
is a model that
Given the current state of the world s of t or your idea of your current state of the world
And an action that you're taking or that someone else is taking
something that you can
Choose or at least observe
And perhaps an auxiliary latent variable z of t which represents
What you don't know about the world. Okay, so the part of the world the state of the world that you don't know or the
Thing that's unpredictable about what's going to go on in the world
The forward model predicts the next state of the world s(t+1). Okay, you discretized
Time in in some way. So if you have
a model of the world
of that type
You can simulate in your head what's going to happen as a consequence of your actions, okay
So you have this uh this model in your head
uh, you know, the current state of the world or
Some idea of the current state of the world you run your internal model of the world forward
With a sequence of a of t which is a sequence of action that you imagine taking
And your model of the world as you imagine it will predict what's going to happen in the world, okay
If you could do this then you could plan a sequence of actions that will arrive at a particular goal
Okay. So for example, what sequence of action should I
Uh should I do to grab this pen?
Um, you know, I should you know, follow a particular trajectory, you know actuate my muscles in a particular way, so I grab this pen
And
The criterion the the the cost function I can measure is is whether i've grabbed the pen. Okay, whether the pen is in my grasp
I could measure this with some some function perhaps
And the question is can I
Plan a sequence of action that given my model of the world which in this case is the model of my hand
And the model of where the pen is
Will allow me to grab it
Okay, it's a little more complicated if I throw the pen and I have to catch it in the air
okay, because I have to predict the trajectory of the pen so I have to have
uh
An intuitive model of physics to be able to uh, grab that pen which of course i've learned through experience as well
People are surprised you like so much reinforcement learning. This is not reinforcement. It has absolutely nothing to do with reinforcement learning, let me
Be very clear. This has nothing to do with reinforcement learning
Uh this may have to do in the future. Okay, but right now it doesn't
um
Model-based reinforcement learning. No, it doesn't has nothing to do with reinforcement learning. Let me okay
Let me let me go through this a little bit. Can you explain the difference then someone asking?
Um in a minute, okay. So now
Uh, so on the left here you have this little agent it has this model of the world that you can run forward
Okay
Uh, it can it has an actor or you can think of it as a policy that produces a sequence of actions
Which is going to feed to the model
and then a critic which is going to predict what the
cost
of the
Final state or the trajectory is going to be according to the criterion. So the critic here computes the
Basically the cost
Of not fulfilling the goal that I set myself
okay, so if I
If my task is to reach for this pen and I kind of miss the pen by a few centimeters
My cost is a few centimeters if I grab it the cost is zero
If I miss it by a lot, the cost is higher. Okay, that would be an example of a cost
Now, okay, so there there is
A number of different things you can do with uh, this sort of basic, uh model of uh intelligent agent
so the first one is
Uh, you start from an initial state that you observe in the world. You run your forward model you give a
A proposal for a sequence of actions you measure the cost
And what you can do here ignoring the the p here which represents a policy. Um
Let's let's imagine it doesn't exist
By gradient descent or by some sort of optimization algorithm. You could you could try to find the sequence of actions
That will minimize the overall cost over the trajectory. I start from the state
I run my forward model
And it it takes an action
Okay, let me just call this a1 this is s1 or s1
And this is going to give me s2 and i'm going to measure the cost of s2 through some cost function
See
Okay, the next time step running my forward model again
Make an action action proposal a2 this is all simulated. This is all in my head
Right because this model this forward model is in my head
See my frontal cortex
So i'm not actually doing this in the world
Etc right so I can unroll this for a few time steps
Those time steps can be milliseconds if I control muscles they can be
Seconds if I control high level actions, they can be hours. Okay, so if I want to plan how to
I don't know go to san francisco. You know, I need to
get to the airports and then catch a plane and then when I arrive there catch a taxi or something, etc
Okay, so this is independent at the the level of which level description of the of the thing
Okay, so what I can do with this is I can do a very classical
method called model predictive control
So it's a classical method of
Optimal control which is a whole discipline that has been around since the the 50s. If not if not earlier
And some of the methods are method predictive controls goes go back to the the 1960s there's something called the kelley bryson algorithm
I think it's kelley with an e i'm not sure
Um, so this is the
Method very similar to the one i'm describing at the moment
and
This was used primarily by
Nasa, let's say to compute trajectories for rockets. Okay, so when they started having computers in the 60s
uh at nasa they
They started computing trajectories with computers and they were basically using things like this
Before that they had to do it by hand, okay
And if you haven't seen the movie, uh hidden figures I um, it describes how people were competing this by hand
This was mostly done by black women black mathematicians
uh women
Mathematicians who also ended up kind of programming those computers watch that movie is it's really great
Um, okay. So here is a basic idea here
Um, this looks very much like a recurrent net
Okay, because your forward model is basically the same network replicated over over time and this is like an unworld recurrent network
and so
Well, what you do here is you back propagate
The value of the cost through this entire network all the way to the actions
And you don't use this for training you use this for inference
You think of the actions as latent variables?
And you basically by gradient descent or some other optimization method
You find a sequence of actions that will minimize the sum of the cost over the trajectory
Okay
So basically you have
An overall
cost
um
I'm going to call it big c and that's going to be the sum over the time step
time steps of the little c of
St
Okay
Uh
And what you're going to do is big a which is the sequence of a is going to be replaced by
its own value minus
some
step size times the gradient of big c with respect to a
Okay, so as long as you can compute the gradient of the sum of those costs over the trajectory with respect to all of the
components of a which means the trajectories of a
You can do this optimization. You don't have to do it necessarily through gradient descent in some cases
There are more efficient ways to do this optimization
um
using dynamic programming for example
If a is discrete that might be more efficient
But but if a is continuous and high dimensional you basically have no choice but to use gradient based methods
Okay, so this is inference. It's not there's no learning yet. What is a
Big a is the sequence
a1 a2
A3 etc
Okay, so you have a differentiable objective function and you can minimize it with respect to the variables you're interested in
So what do you get out of this?
There are no weights in a a is a vector, right? So a is a vector. Yeah
Yeah, so that was actually because we never use uh, we never minimize vectors so far. We always been minimizing
We are always being optimizing weights. So people are oh we have
For latent variables like the z variables the latent variables of the energy-based models the latent variables
We do minimize the energy with respect to z. So this is the same problem here
We're solving. I think yeah, I think not everyone understood that the latent variables are actually inputs. So that was I think like
also misunderstanding with the
Question we had on piazza about training these
These uh latent variable models. Yeah, you don't want to use the word training for latent variables or for things like this
because
Uh, you want to use inference
Okay, you want to use the word "to infer" not "to train". I want to use the word inference not training
What's the difference between inference and training?
Training
With training you learn a a parameter
Uh, that is the same for a large number of samples
Okay
for inference
You find the value of some variable a latent variable a in this case z in the case of a latent variable energy-based model
uh
That is specific to one sample
Okay, you change the sample the written variable changes so you don't learn it because you don't remember it from one time
to the next
You know, there's no memory for it, right? Um
So that's the difference, you know conceptually you're doing the same kind of operation where you do learning and inference
And so at some level of abstraction, they're the same
But uh inference you do it per sample
learning you do it, uh
Over a bunch of samples and the parameter is shared across the samples
When we have an energy based model, and we'd like to do inference
We still have a minimization to do at every time we perform this. Uh, we use it, right
So that was a big difference between... After you after you've trained the model when you use it
You you still have to do minimization with respect to the latent variables. Okay
So that's the big difference same here
here, uh there may or may not be any training your forward model may be built by hand or maybe trained but by the time
we're here It's trained. We're not training anything here. We're just doing inference. We're figuring out
What is the optimal value of the sequence of a is that we'll minimize for
uh
for cost
Overall cost and this is an inference problem just like energy-based models
For example, the fm the forward model can be just a one line of equation of physics, right? It can be just a deterministic equation
so imagine the forward model is the few equations that describe the the uh,
The the physics of a rocket and a is basically the action on the the steering
you know how you orient the nozzles and then the the thrust
So that would be the the collection of a would be the collection of those variables and then there is you know
very simple physics newtonian physics, basically
Uh, you can write the equations it will give you the state of the rocket at the next
uh time step
Uh, as a function of state of rocket at the previous time step and the actions you're taking that's how you do simulations
That's how every simulator
works
And then your cost function if you want to shoot a rocket would be maybe a combination of two things one, uh would be the
the uh
Energy spent during that time step. Okay, the amount of fuel you spent something like that
and the second term might be the distance to a target you want to reach maybe you want to rendezvous with a space station and
uh
The the second term in the cost would be the distance to the space station. Okay square distance to the space station
uh if you measure the um,
The sum over the entire trajectory of the distance to the space station the system will try to minimize the time
It will take to get to the space station because they will want to minimize
The sum of the square of the distances to the space station over the trajectory
But at the same time it wants to minimize fuel so you have to balance those two terms, right?
So that's a classical way of doing optimal control and that's called model predictive control
Is model is kalman filtering one type of model predictive control
No kalman filtering is a particular, uh forward model if you want. It's a way of estimating the state of the world
Okay
but um
It's you know, basically given your observation of the state of the world through a perception system
There's going to be some uncertainty about the state of the world
And the kalman filter basically assumes a gaussian distribution on this uncertainty
And now when you run through your forward model
You're going to have a resulting uncertainty about the state of the world at the next time step
because
It wasn't certain to start with
Okay
So given the uncertainty when you started from where you started from, what's the uncertainty after one step of physics if you want
And if you assume linearity of all those steps and gaussianity of the uncertainty that's what uh, that's what the
kalman filter
Is. um most of the uncertainty comes from okay, so now now your forward model produces
A prediction and then the next time step you might get another reading of the state of the world because your sensors are still working
so now you have two gaussians one is
your new perception of the world tells you here is where I think
The state of the world is and your forward model also predicted here is why I think it what where I think it is
and you have to combine those two that's where the complexity of common filtering comes in which is uh i've got
two gaussian predictions
so the resulting probability distribution is also a gaussian if you compute the covariance matrix and et cetera, and that's where the
the formulas for um kalman filters come from
Okay, so kalman filter is a way to deal with the uncertainty
in the
reading your perception of the world and in the uh,
uh
When you propagate this uncertainty in your forward model
Uh, I think there was still a main difference, I think you wanted to address the point that the this is different from RL(reinforcement learning)
Okay, so what is RL in that context? Okay, so
Okay, I need I need I need one more step before I talk about rl okay
And here is that step
Okay, so what we had uh, just a minute ago was a forward model that's enrolled in time
And the system has
Takes a sequence of actions a1 a2 a3
S1 s2 and then we have the cost function here coming up
Okay, and this this could go on right
now
What we'd like to be able to do
Is not have to do this optimization with respect to a1 a2 a3 a4
uh every time every time we need to do a planning we don't want to have to
go through this complex process of back propagating a gradient through this entire system to do model predictive. Uh,
Control
And so a simple way to get rid of that step
Is the same trick that we use in auto encoders versus sparse coding. So remember it's sparse coding we wanted to
Reconstruct, but then we had to do inference with respect to the latent variable by optimization
and that turned out to be
To be expensive. So we talked about last week was the idea of using an encoder that we trained to predict the optimal value directly
Okay, and we're going to do the same here
That resulted in the idea as part of the sparse encoder. We're going to do the same here
I'm going to train a network to take the state
and directly
Predict what the optimal value of the action is and this network. Of course, we're going to apply every time step
And this is going to be called a policy network
Okay, so the policy network takes the state
and produces a guess
about the best action
to take at
At this time so as to minimize the overall cost, okay
And this is going to be a trainable neural net
Or whatever model parametrized model that we want. the way we're going to train this model is basically just back back propagation
okay, so we're going to
Uh using our perception module this is this is the this is the world here
and
We're looking at the world with a camera
And there's a perception module that gives us a guess as to what the state of the world is
Okay, this is perception
And this is a forward model applied multiple time steps
And this is our cost
Okay, so what we can do
is
run the system
And to run the system we first
Run through the perception
We compute
an
Action, we run this action through the forward model. This forward model gives us here is the next state
We're going to be in compute the cost
And then keep going
Okay, keep doing this
Just forward prop through this entire system, which is really kind of an unrolled recurrent net if you want
And once you're done you back propagate gradient gradients from the all the terms in the cost function
all the way through the network all the way through the parameters of
That policy network
Okay, so basically you compute
uh
D of big c so big c remember is the sum of all the c's
a long time
with respect to d w
okay, and that's just going to be the sum over time of
The big c over dw
Sorry, yeah big c over d
a
t
d a t over d w
Okay. I've just applied chain rule right, but I don't need to right if I just you know
Define this function in pytorch and just do backprop. It'll just do the right thing
um, so
I can compute the gradient of the overall cost with respect to the parameters of that policy network
And so if I train this over sufficiently many
uh
Samples if my forward model is correct
if my cost function does what I want then my policy network is going to learn a good policy that
Just looking at the state will minimize the expected cost over trajectory
Okay
The average cost over a trajectory. There's no reinforcement learning here. This is all
backprop, okay
Now we can talk about the difference with reinforcement learning the main difference with reinforcement learning here
Is uh is is twofold. The first one is in reinforcement learning
In most reinforcement training scenarios at least the
The c function is a black box. Well, it's a black box not a red box
Okay, that's the first difference the second difference is that this is not a forward model of the world this is the real world
And your measure of the state of the world is imperfect so inside of this policy network you might have a perception network here
That estimates the state of the world so you have no control over the real world
And your cost function is not
Known you can you can just get the output of the cost function by just trying something, right?
You take an action you see the effect on the world
and that gives you
uh
What reinforcement running people call a reward but it's just a negative cost
Okay is the value of negative value of your cost
But the cost is not differentiable you don't know the function of the cost you have to go through the world
To figure out the value of the cost
Okay
Um, and that's the that's that's the main issue with reinforcement running which is that the cost function is not differentiable
Uh, it's it's unknown
The only way to estimate it is by trying something and then observing the value which is what the reward is really it's a negative
The negative of the reward is basically your your cost. Okay?
So in that situation since you cannot evaluate gradients
To minimize your cost you have to try multiple things
You have to try an action see the result and then try another action see if the result is better
And then try another action see if the result is better
And if your cost function is very flat
You have to try many many things before you get a non-zero reward or you know, a non-high cost
And so that's that's where the the complexity goes. There is the additional problem of
exploration, so
um
You know you because you don't know the the form of the of the cost and because it's non-differentiable
uh
You might need to kind of try many actions in kind of a smart way to figure out
In which part of the space to go to be able to sort of figure out how can I improve my uh my performance?
Okay, so that's the the main issue
uh of uh
Uh exploration and then there is the issue of uh, exploration versus exploitation. So the fact that um,
When you're on a situation, you don't want to take completely random actions because they're likely to not result in anything interesting
So you want to take actions that are kind of close to what you think might work?
uh and sort of you know
occasionally kind of try something else
While you're learning and learn your policy as you go
What i'm describing what I was describing just before
Is a situation where you can do all of this in your head because you have a model of the world
And you can optimize your sequence of action very efficiently because you have a differentiable cost function
Your cost function is computed by your your own brain if you want inside of your agent
You can tell if you grab the pen you can tell the distance between your hand and the pen
So you can compute your own cost function and it is kind of in your internal world model is differentiable in the real world
It's not
In the real world, you don't know the derivative
of the distance of your hand to the pen unless you have some model of that in your head, but
By default you don't but because everything is in your head, everything is differentiable. Everything is implemented by neural net and everything
You can back properly gradient to everything
So that's the big advantage of this kind of approach versus reinforcement planning. Okay, make everything differentiable
So there's two problems with the world. So there's one big advantage in this kind of this kind of scenario
uh
which is you can run this faster than real time because your forward model inside of your
Agent can run as fast as you want. You don't need to
Run through the world. Okay, that's one advantage. Second advantage is the actions you're taking
Will not kill you
because
You can predict
Uh, using your forward model, you know, maybe you'll predict that the action will kill you
But you're not going to take it in the real world. So
It won't kill you
If you have an accurate forward model
Third advantage because everything takes place in your head. Everything is internet. Everything is differentiable
you can use all kinds of efficient, uh learning or
Inference algorithms to figure out a good course of actions
Okay
so
That's the difference with with reinforcement training in refreshment running
You're telling yourself
I have to go through the real world
uh
I don't have a model of the real world. I don't know how to compute the cost function in a differentiable way
That said a lot of reinforcement learning methods
Actually work by training a model of the cost function
Okay, so actor critic methods
basically
the role of the critic
uh is to learn to evaluate to kind of predict the value of the
Overall objective function the expected value of the objective function
And because it's a it's a neural net that you're going to train. You can back backpropagate gradient to it
So you're basically learning an approximation of the cost function of the real world
Of the real world using using a neural net. That's that's the role of a critic
Okay, why is it so good to have models when you're learning a
Skill like learning to drive for example
It's basically what
Allows you to learn quickly and to learn without killing yourself
So if you don't have a good model of the world, you don't know about gravity. You don't know about the dynamics of objects
uh, you don't know anything and
You put an agent at the at the wheel of a car. The agent has no idea what the physics of a car is
Okay, and you put the car next to a cliff?
The car is driving at you know, 30 miles an hour next to next to a cliff
The agent doesn't have a model of the world has no idea that by turning the wheel to the right
The car will run off the cliff and will fall into the into the ravine
It has to actually try it to figure it out
It has to fall into the ravine to figure out that this is a bad idea
Okay
And maybe just from one sample. It's not going to be able to learn it
So it's going to have to run into the ravine like thousands of times before it figures out
the model of the world that first turning the wheel to the right makes the car go to the right and second that when the
Car goes above a ravine it falls into a ravine and destroys itself
Okay, if you have a model of the world that understands about gravity and things like this
Then you know that turning the wheel to the right is going to make the car fall into the ravine
And you don't do it because you know, it's going to kill you
okay, so it allows humans and animals to learn quickly much much quicker than any uh
Model-free reinforcement learning methods that has ever been devised is is the fact that we have very very good world models in our head
Okay
Now what does that tell us? Um
Okay. So here is the problem with with the world. The world is not deterministic
Or if it is deterministic
It's so complex that
It equally well could be non-deterministic. It doesn't make any difference for us
There's two problems with predicting the next state of the world the first problem is
That the world is not entirely predictable
And it could be not entirely predictable for two reasons. Those are called
aleatoric uncertainty and epistemic uncertainty. aleatoric uncertainty
Is due to the fact that the world is intrinsically
unpredictable
Or the fact that we don't have full information about the state of the world, so we cannot predict exactly what's going to happen next
so
You're looking at me right now. You've a pretty good model of the immediate environment of of me
okay, but you cannot exactly predict in which way i'm going to move my head next because you don't have an accurate model of what's
inside my skull
Okay your perceptual system
does not give you a full model of
how my brain functions uh, unfortunately
So
So you cannot exactly predict what i'm, you know?
What i'm going to do next what i'm going to say i'm going to move my head et cetera
So, that's aleatoric
uncertainty, there is also epistemic uncertainty epistemic uncertainty is the fact that you can't
completely predict the next
uh state of the world
Because the amount of training data you've had is not was not enough
Your model hasn't been trained enough to really kind of figure it out
Okay, that's kind of a different
uh type of
uncertainty
So the big question now is though. How do we train models of the world under uncertainty. I give you
An s(t)
Can you predict s(t+1)?
And it's the same problem we encountered before we start supervising. I give you an x. Can you predict y?
But the problem is that there are now multiple y's that are compatible with x the multiple
S(t+1)s are compatible with s even for a given action
So, what does that mean that means that our model here our forward model
May take the state of the world and an action, but it will also have to take
A latent variable which we don't know the value of to predict the next state
Okay, and this looks very much like what we talked about earlier where we had
I'm going to draw this in a different topology, but it's the same idea
So we had x
And it was going through
a predictor
Computing h and then that was going through
A decoder that will take into account a latent variable to predict
Y-bar and then we observe y
Okay, this is a prediction for s and maybe
at some time
We might be able to
Actually take the action and observe the next state of the world while we are training our model
We'll actually be observing the next state of the world
T plus one
Okay, so to train a forward model here we we take the state st
We take an action if we have an action
Uh, we have a latent variable and our prediction goes into a cost function
That diagram is exactly identical to the one on the right
Right, it's the same it's exactly the same diagram except I split the
Fm into two modules
Okay, i've given it a particular
Architecture. In fact I could make this
uh more explicit
I think you have the super thick marker selected. I do. Yes, you don't like that, huh?
So this would be my forward model
Okay, so that's what's inside this box uh inside of the forward model box here is this
And you know I renamed uh,
S(t) Is now called x and s t plus one is not called y bar. But I mean it's not for y
But it's the same thing otherwise, right? So it's the same scenario that we talked about before in latent variable energy-based models, essentially
But now we're going to use this to train, uh a forward model to predict what's going to happen in the world
So
Um
We may have to play the same tricks that that we played uh that we talked about last week
Which is that, um
Last week what we explained was that we can take
Okay, the way I drew this last week was slightly different
Um
what explained last week is that we can
if we have while we are training our forward model, we have a pair x and y
And the way we find the value of z is by minimizing the energy with respect to z right so we basically find
z star
Which is the argmin
Of c of y and y-bar, y-bar being the output of our of our predictor of our system
Okay
And then we do one step of gradient descent, so we change the parameters of our entire system according to the gradient of
uh
that cost but for this to work we had to regularize z
limit, its information content
And we have to do the same here
Why is that? well here we're we're trying to solve a prediction problem but
Imagine and we talked about this a couple weeks ago
I give you an x and a y and you find the z that minimizes the overall energy and the z is not regularized
if z is the same dimension as y the there's probably going to be
A z for any y that makes the cost function zero
right if there's enough capacity in z
There's always going to be a value of z that makes the cost function zero
And that's bad because that means my energy function is going to be completely flat
It's going to be zero everywhere and I need it to be small on the training samples and high
outside of the region of high data density
and what we saw in the last couple weeks is that by regularizing z limiting its capacity either by
Making it sparse for example or making it discrete or by
Making it noisy then we can limit this capacity. Why do we need zt If you already have at
Well, so at is the action you take right
um
Okay
i'm going to tell you i'm going to
I'm going to let this pen go
Okay, but you don't know which direction it's going to
It's going to go right so let's say it goes this way
But I have to predict in advance which way it's going to go. It's like okay, here's a better situation you are uh,
Uh, you're a goalie playing soccer
Okay
And it's a penalty kick. So you're in front of the
you know the kicker in front of
You and the guy is going to kick the ball and you're going to have to jump one way or the other
And you have to make a choice. Am I jumping left or right?
And you have to make that decision based on what you observe from the person but you don't know exactly
What the ball is going to do a is which direction you do you jump in? I mean, it's basically how you jump
z is
What you don't know about the player in front of you doing. Okay, you don't know the state of the world
You don't know the state of the brain of this guy
And so you don't know if he's going to shoot left or right or up or down?
Okay
That's the difference right, z is what you cannot
Know about the world that is necessary to make the prediction of the next state a is the action you take
Which in this case has very little influence on the immediate state of the world. Yeah, it seems it seems to be clear now
right, so
You need to regularize z and then one of the tricks we uh, we described
um
So so the one of the things we described to regularize z was was passivity another one was adding noise
Um
But the other trick we described is this idea of having an encoder right so
You have x or st
Run through
The predictor the predictor goes into
the decoder
which makes a prediction about
Y. Let's call it y bar
And you compare oops, sorry
You compare y bar to y
And here you have z and what we talked about is the idea of using an encoder here
To predict the optimal value of z
And then basically having a cost function that
Is determining the energy that measures the discrepancy between the value of z you actually use and the value of z predicted by the encoder
And perhaps this is regularized
in some way
And the predictor also has to influence the encoder
So it's pretty clear that you need, uh an information bottleneck
uh
between the encoder the decoder
Otherwise the system will cheat it will completely ignore x
You will be able to predict y exactly by just cheating by looking at the value of y
Running it through the encoder and then running it through the decoder and then predicting y right? That's just a very simple encoder
So unless you restrict the capacity of z the system will just cheat and not actually train itself to predict
You have to push down on the information content
Of z so as to force the system to use uh the information from x
Okay to make the the best prediction
Okay, now we can use that trick to to uh, uh to train our forward model
Because again a forward model is basically just an instance of this
And and this is uh the project that uh,
uh for autonomous driving that uh,
my former student Mikael Henaff, uh worked on and uh Alfredo has worked on this and is still working on this project
And so here you're trying to train a car to drive itself
And
What's difficult to predict what is what the car around you are going to do?
So you place a camera above a highway and you watch the the cars kind of go by
And you can track every car
And then extract the immediate neighborhood of the car, basically
a little rectangle around every car that indicates where the other cars are relative to the
to your car
And this is what's represented at the bottom. Um, so at the bottom you
You have a little rectangle that's centered around a given car
and then all the cars around are
the uh
You know a little rectangular centered on that car where the car is
in a
Standardized location in the middle of that rectangle you do this for every car
What it gives you is for every car a sequence of what the cars around it are going to do
And we can use this to train a forward model
That will predict what the cars around us are going to do
The question is if this forward model is predicting all possible futures, uh, irrespective of the action taken, yeah
Where we predict a set of futures so given one action and
So given one initial state one action and one particular value of the latent variable will make a single prediction
And then you can vary the latent variable and you will make multiple predictions. You can change the action, of course
right
so
I've redrawn the little diagram I drew previously here here. The the state basically is a sequence of three frames from this video
um
There's no abstract state here. It's just the
the
Picture itself. The blue car is is our car and the green cars are the other cards
so you take kind of three frames from the past run this through this, uh,
Neural net which attempts to predict the next uh the next frame
okay using a
Basically a big convolutional net as a predictor and a big convolutional net as a decoder
But there's a latent variable here. There's also an action here, which is not drawn
That gets into this
And the system also has an encoder
So it looks more like this
There's a and again the action here is not represented but
Imagine there is one
So x is the the past frames it goes through a predictor that predicts a representation of the input
And then that representation
goes into
a convolutional net that
the decoder that predicts it basically
Is combined additively
With a latent variable so it's added to a latent variable
Before going into a decoder that makes a prediction for the next state
And the latent variable itself is a latent variable, but
Is being predicted by by an encoder
which itself is also a convolutional net it takes the past and the
And the future and tries to predict the ideal value of the latent variable
now, of course
You have to restrict the information content here. And this is done in this particular project using sort of a VAE like approach
where the
Um, I mean, it's basically a VAE
with a few a few tricks
So z is sampled from a distribution that is obtained
From the output of the encoder the output of the encoder outputs a prediction for z bar as well as prediction for variances
And z is sampled from the from that distribution so it's not optimized. It's sampled
But there's also a term that tries to kind of minimize the sum of the square of the zs over time, uh, which is the
standard
uh technique for vae
And that goes into the decoder
And so this is trained as a conditional autoencoder. Basically, there's another trick that's added to this, which is that
Half the time z is simply set to zero so half the time the system is told you're not allowed to use z
Just make your best guess as the prediction without a z
and that drives the system to sort of really kind of use the past in sort of a bigger way than if you just uh
Have a noisy z if you just use the standard
The vae type training the system basically ignores the the past it just cheats. It looks at the
The answer y
I will cover the rest in a greater detail in a lab in a future lab, uh
Perhaps you want to say something about the GANs?
Because I will be actually going over this the whole presentation as well you are
so GANs are a
particular form of contrastive learning
okay, so remember that uh when we talked about energy-based learning
we Have
data points
And our model which i'm going to
Draw like this
With a cost function it could have any kind of structure but i'm just going to draw it like this
So this would be sort of a reconstruction type
Model right. So imagine that the model here is an auto encoder or something like this, but you can imagine just about just about anything
A simplified version. I mean a more general version of this would be just
y goes into
A cost function and i'm not specifying
what the cost function looks like
Okay
So what the cost function computes is a in the space of y so, let's say y is two dimensional
Is an energy that we want to be low on the data and high outside the data
And here I deliberately drew a bad energy function, right so this energy function is bad because
It should be low around this region where we have data and it should be higher outside and right now it's it's pretty low
In in this region right here
So we talked about contrastive methods and contrastive methods consist in taking a sample
And pushing down on its energy
And then taking a contrastive sample
Which i'm going to draw in purple
so contrastive sample should be
A sample that our model already gives low energy to but should not give low energy to we're going to push that up. Okay
So push up on the energy of this guy
Push down on the energy of that guy and if you keep picking those samples and those contrastive samples well,
By minimizing some objective function that wants to make the energy of the blue point small and the energy of the
pink points high
then the system will
will learn
properly
So we've seen several ways of generating contrasting samples the idea of denoising autoencoder
Which is to take a sample and basically corrupt it in some way
we've seen the idea of
Contrasting divergence which takes a sample and then you go down the energy
With some noise and that gives you a contracting sample to push up
um
And you know we've seen
A number of other methods that are based on prior knowledge about similarity between between samples
But here is here is another idea
The other idea is to use is to train a neural net to produce those contrastive samples intelligently, and that's the basic idea of GANs
at least in a form of GANs that
Would be called energy-based gans. You can do several formulations against in fact, there's an entire laundry list of various types of gans
but the basic idea of gans is is that you
You train your energy model. So the energy model in the context of gann is called a discriminator or sometimes a critic
But it's basically just very similar to an energy model
And you train it to take low energy on the data points
and then you
Train another net neural net to generate contrastive data points and you move their energy up
Okay
so the overall
Diagram is something like this
You have
a discriminator and the discriminator really should be
Not drawn this way. It could be a large neural net
But in the end oops, sorry
In the end it's just a cost function
Okay, so it takes it takes a variable y
And it tells you it's good or bad low energy if it's good high energy if it's bad
So in one phase
you collect a piece of data from the from your data set and just give it to
your discriminator
Okay, so this is a real y coming from data
That's a training sample
and you say the output of
of that
Should go down. Okay, I should really write this as f
Because after all, it's just it's an energy function
Okay, so make f of y go down
Of course by changing the parameters right so you do w replace by w minus eta
Df
So f is a neural net? f is a neural net
Okay, some parametrized function, but probably a neural net probably a pretty complicated neural net
Okay, that's the first, uh
first thing
And that will make the energy of data points small, okay
Now there's a form of this that's conditional. So the form of this that's conditional you have an extra input here
Which is an observation, okay, but you can have this or not that's called conditional again. It doesn't
Matter. Okay second phase
Or for contrastive samples
uh, you have a latent variable z
That you sample from some distribution a distribution that's easy to sample from let's say a gaussian
multi-multivariate gaussian
Or uniform or something you run this through what's called a generator
So this is a neural net and that neural net produces
Something similar to y okay, it just produces an image. Let's say y bar images
And again, you run this through your discriminator
But now you want to make that
Large
Okay, so in fact what I told you before is a lie
Uh, you don't do this update like that
Okay, but here what you want is you want to make
Fw of this y bar high
Okay
And what you're going to do now is train the discriminator and the generator simultaneously
So you're going to first have to come up with a cost function a loss function
And this loss function is going to be you know sum um, you know a sum over samples
Of a per sample loss function that
Basically is a function of
f of y
And f of y bar
Where y bar of course is generated from the randomly sampled latent variable z
Now this cost function needs to be a decreasing function of f of y and an increasing function of f of y bar
Okay, you can use just about any cost function you want
As long as it makes for y decrease and it makes f of y bar increase
Or as long as it makes a difference
Decrease f of y minus f of y bar, a good example of this
Would be kind of a hinge loss for example
Okay
So something that says my loss function
is going to be
f of y
Plus
Some margin minus
f of y bar
Positive part, okay. So this is a this is a hinge
And it says
I want to make f of y bar smaller than
M. Um, other than that, I don't care
Uh bigger than m. I'm sorry, I drew this backwards
So overall as a function of f of y bar this function looks like this
okay, so it wants to make f of y bar larger than M
Okay. So that's an example the the actual cost function that most uh, the original formulation of gans used
basically plugs, uh each of those terms into a sigmoid and tries to make
the
you know the the sigmoid applied to f of y as close to one as possible and sigma applied to f uh
Y bar as close to zero as possible. It's you know, it's basically that nothing more than that. So it's
sigmoid of f of y
Plus one minus sigmoid of
Uh
f of y bar and
you you you take logs because
Um, I mean, this is not the loss function
This is kind of what goes before the loss function, so this is kind of like a cross entropy
but you have cross entropy that's positive for the
the positive phase and sort of the
The target is negative for the negative phase. Um
Yeah, I shouldn't write it this way this is wrong actually sorry about that
But you put it the logistic loss for each of those so it's technically
You know log of 1 plus exponential f of y
for the correct one and
Minus for that log f1 plus
e to the
f of y
Plus log
One plus e to the minus f of y bar
But you could imagine a large number of objective functions of this type
Okay
So this is the loss function you're going to use to train the discriminator
But the generator this is for the discriminator
But it's going to be a loss function for the generator and that's a different loss function
And you're going to optimize those two loss functions the same way
the one for the generator is is one that
basically
Wants to make the generator produce outputs that the discriminator thinks are good, but they're not
Okay, so basically the generator, um
Uh
Wants to
Adapt its its weight
So that the output that it produces y bar
Produces a low energy for f y
Okay
so
You sample
A random variable z you run it through the generator
It produces a y bar you run through the discriminator, the f of y you get some value and then you back propagate the value
through the generator
and adapt the weights to the generator so that
This energy goes down. Okay. So basically the generator is trying to find a white bar that has low energy as low as possible
Okay, and it trains itself to kind of produce wise to have low energy again if if we're talking about
Conditional GANs there's going to be
An x variable that's going to enter those two modules, but that makes no difference in the end
So Lg is maybe simply an increasing function
Of
f of y bar
I think we are kind of running out of time. We are
We have run out of time
So this would be uh, some objective function of
f of
g if g is the generator of z where z is sampled randomly
Okay, so you just do back prop to this and you change the parameters of g, let's call them u
So that this goes down now, this is called
This is called a game in a sense that you have two objective functions that you need to minimize simultaneously and they are
incompatible with each other
And so it's not a gradient descent problem. You have to find
What's called a nash equilibrium between those two functions?
And gradient descent will not do it
uh
By default, so that leads to
Instabilities and there is tons of papers on how to make GANs actually work
That's kind of a complicated part, but alfredo will tell you all about this, uh tomorrow
Maybe you also you want to mention the uh, the one with the sigmoid that creates some issues. Uh,
If we have like samples that are close to the true manifold
Yes
and then I think we can close the
Conclusion. Okay, so
Let me mention that so let's imagine that your data
So again, uh energy-based framework
Your data is around some manifold but it's a thin manifold so it's an infinitely thin distribution
Okay
In the original formulation of gan the the gan the discriminator would need to produce
Zero probability outside of this
Okay, so it needs to produce zero probability here
And it needs to produce
On the manifold in this part to produce infinite probability
In such a way that
The integral if this is really a density estimation in such a way that the integral of this density over the entire space is one
And this is of course
very hard
So gans basically abandoned the idea of actually learning a distribution
What they want to do is produce zero the original formulation produce zero outside the manifold of data
and produce
one here
It's the output of the sigmoid that needs to be one which means the weighted sum going into that sigmoid
It needs to be infinite essentially. So it's not that different
Um, and the problem with this is that if you train the system successfully
And you get that energy function, which is zero outside the data manifold and one on the data manifold. Your energy function is completely useless
It's useless because it's a golf course right? It's flat
so the energy function basically that corresponds to this would be the negative log of that right so it would be
It would be infinity here
and
the minimum value of your cost function on the manifold which for example could be zero if it
If it's if it's an auto encoder the energy gonna be smaller than zero, right?
Um, and so it's a it's a it's a golf course of infinite altitude, which is really not that useful
What you want
As I said before for every energy-based model if you want an energy-based model to be useful you want the energy function to be smooth
You don't want it to go to infinity in sort of
a very small step you want it to be smooth so that you can do inference so that if
You start from a point here. It's easy to find
A point on the manifold that's nearby using and descent for example, right?
so the original formulation of gan leads to
First of all infinite weights in the discriminator instabilities something called mode collapse, which alfredo will tell you about
And in the end
A contrast function an energy function that's essentially useless
So it's not
ideally formulated so people have proposed ways to fix it by regularizing the
Energy function basically forcing it to be smooth. So one good example of this is something called wasserstein gans
Proposed by Martin Arjovsky who just graduated from NYU
And Lon Bottou and Soumith Chintala.
And and the idea of of that is to basically limit the size of the weights of the discriminator so that the function
is smooth and there is, you know, various mathematical arguments, uh
In probabilistic framework, but that's the basic idea and there's lots of variations of this also
Questions about today class it was dense, but at least we were, you know answering every question
it was coming right through so I think we
We follow along today
um, I wasn't sure if maybe you like
explained it in a different form and I didn't realize it's the same thing, but I was a little um
Lost on what the policy network is?
Okay, what that does?
So the policy network takes the estimation of the state of the world and produces an action
and it's trained to
minimize the expected cost
of uh
The state over the over a trajectory, but it takes just one action, okay
So, right and there was a there was a part towards the end where I guess you drew a new connection
um
right that uh from like s to
Uh where it goes
down
to like
connected through some module to a
So what is happening there? So the policy network is the indicated by pi here on the screen
So it takes s the state
And it produces an action
Okay
Okay. Okay. That's what a policy is, right. You observe the state of the world and you take an action?
I see okay
in fact
a probabilistic policy is you don't take an action you give a
distribution over actions and then you pick the action in some way and perform that distribution but here
You know, you just have to take an action
If the number of actions is discrete then uh this this pi network is this policy network is basically a classifier
And it produces a bunch of scores for each possible action, and then you take one of the actions
Probabilistically or deterministically deterministically you just take the action with the highest score
Uh probabilistically you can sample according to to the score
And then you run through your forward model and you keep going
okay, so without the policy connection then
then the action is just kind of
It's a latent variable. So you have to optimize with respect to the latent variable to find the to find its optimal value
So you have this this kind of uh diagram now
where
the actions are not produced by a neural net they
There are latent variables that you have to figure out for every new every every time you run your model you
You have to figure out what's the best sequence of action to minimize my cost? And so you have to basically
uh, do do this for example by grading descent figuring out the sequence of a that will minimize the sum of the c's over the
trajectory
that's that's called model predictive control and then um
the one with the policy network
um
Is is called, uh, you know, direct uh control essentially
Um professor uh
You say that during inference we need to uh minimize
The energy
to get the final value but
Uh, okay. There are two questions one won't it take too much time during inference and
Would be useful for real-time systems
and the second one is
Since it's unrolled and you have to back propagate all the way through the beginning
Yeah have all the problems that we face in
uh recurrent neural networks
exactly, so
Presumably you're not going to get the same problems as you have with current nets because your forward model
You know
Presumably implements the dynamics of some real systems. So
It might not have the issues
Of sort of non-invertibility that you have if it's a physical system. It's probably going to be
reversible so you may not have the
Same issue as with regular recurrent nets but uh, but yeah, you're facing this in the same problems
now, uh
In real time situations you you use a form of this called
receding horizon planning
Planning
Okay, so receding horizon planning, uh is when you are in a it's a real time situation
Uh, your your system will run its forward model for a few steps in the future
I don't know. Let's say a few seconds. Okay, sufficiently many steps to predict for a few seconds
That's your horizon
Uh, then you do this, uh model predictive control
You know by optimizing finding the optimal a that minimizes your cost your estimated cost according to your model
Okay, you know you haven't taken an action yet. Okay, you've just run your internal model to make that prediction
um, so
Through optimization with respect to a you find the sequence of a that optimizes your cost and then you take the first action
in that a
And then you do it again, okay
So with the a you took, observe the state of the world now you have a new
state
Okay, which you observe from your your sensors and now repeat the process run your forward model a number of steps in the future
Optimize the sequence of actions to minimize your cost take the first action
And do it again
So it can be expensive if your horizon is long if your forward model is complicated
um, and so that's when you need
A policy network. So the policy network, basically
Compiles this whole process into a neural net that directly produces
the best action from the state
okay, which may or may not be possible but
It gives you a good guess, now
to give you a concrete example
This is an interesting series of books by
A nobel prize-winning economist that lives in new york called. Daniel Kahneman
And he talks about two systems in the human
Mind called system one and system two so system one
is the
Process by which you take an action without thinking okay
um
You're a very experienced driver and you can drive your car without even paying attention by you know, talking to someone next to you
You don't actually need to think about it. Okay?
System two is more sort of deliberate planning. So
System two is when you use your internal model of the world to kind of predict in advance. What's gonna happen?
Ahead sort of foresee what's gonna happen and then take a deliberate
Uh action that you think is gonna be the right one according to your model. So it's more like reasoning
Okay, you can think of this
You know optimization with respect to actions to minimize an objective as a form of reasoning and we talked about this before
so
uh, basically
Model predictive control is when you don't have a policy you haven't learned the skill
You know what your cost function is you have a pretty good model of the world, but you don't know how to react, okay
So a beginner chess player would be like that
You you look at the the chase game and you have to think about all possibilities before you play
Because you know, you don't know where to play. So you have to kind of imagine all the possibilities
If you are an expert player and you play against a a beginner
You know immediately what to play. You don't have to think about it. I don't know if you've played simultaneous games against
A master or grandmaster at chess grandmaster can play against 50 people and beat them in a few minutes
Because the player can go from just you know one
Opponent to another and just immediately play just it's completely reactive
um, he actually doesn't need to to think because
You know, they've kind of compiled that if you if you want in their
In their knowledge of chess that they don't need to think when you see this
kind of type of easy situation
So that's going from system two to system one
And uh when you learn the skill at first you're hesitant and you have to think about it, you know
You're heads-up. When you drive you drive slowly and you look at everything and you pay attention and then when you
are uh
Experimented you you can just react really quickly. Basically you've gone from model predictive control to
Basically training your own policy network if you will, okay?
And in the process of doing this your uh, your skill has gone from a sort of deliberate planned
conscious
uh
decision mechanism to a sort of subconscious
Automatic uh decision mechanism, that's what sort of acquiring expertise does
And that's that's how you go from this diagram
To that diagram where you have a policy that directly predicts the action without having to plan
Okay, got it, thanks